Intercollegiate Athletics - PAC-10 and NCAA Records 1954-1983
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Intercollegiate Athletics - PAC-10 and NCAA Records
1954-1983
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Archives 219
7 linear feet 8 containers
Included are correspondence, eligibility petitions, letters of intent, meeting minutes, financial information, and booklets from 1954 to 1983.
Organizational History:
The principal contact of the University and the athletics conferences and associations is the faculty representative. The faculty representative from Washington State University originally worked with the Athletic Association of Western Universities (AAWU). The conference changed its name to the Pacific Athletic Conference (PAC-8) in 1968, and then to the PAC-10 in 1978. The representative was responsible for representing WSU in conference meetings and official functions, as well as rules interpretation and compliance. He was the channel for athletes to petition conference and/or NCAA (National Collegiate Athletic Association) rules. He also headed many search committees, and was a member of the University Athletic Council, which advised on internal athletic issues.
Wallis Beasley served as representative through 1966, and Edward Bennett, a professor in the history department, took over thereafter.
The records cover roughly the years 1960-1982, with some material both before and after these dates. All the sections are not complete--there are many gaps. Included are correspondence, eligibility petitions, letters of intent, meeting minutes, financial information, and booklets.
The records are arranged as three series: WSU, AAWU/PAC-8/PAC-10, and NCAA. The files have been arranged chronologically logically in separate sections within each. Material that was attached together (i.e. stapled or paper clipped) has been left together, even if the dates are not in chronological order.
Maintaining the arrangement of the papers as received was not possible as portions were unfiled or of disrupted filing. Thus, some sections are the same as when they arrived, others are not. The records are arranged in three series: WSU, AAWU/PAC-8/ PAC-10, and NCAA, which reflects of the original order of the more-ordered part of the papers. Unfiled materials were assigned to their apparent place in these series. It was difficult at times to distinguish between these three areas consistently, but generally the material in the WSU area includes all correspondence pertaining to WSU specifically, whether in internal WSU, conference, or NCAA correspondence. The conference and NCAA areas are arranged in the same manner. As a general rule, anyone searching the records should examine all three series.
Wide examination is especially important in the case of the WSU women's athletics correspondence. This is a separate subseries in part, but the separation between this and the general WSU correspondence seemed arbitrary at times. As a result, information pertaining to women's athletics, particularly the so-called Title IX requirements, can be found in the general WSU correspondence section, as well as among meeting minutes. The subseries specific to WSU women's athletics includes correspondence from the AIAW (Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women) and the NCAA.
Many items among the records are stapled or otherwise attached to documents in ways that do not follow the filing logic and would seem to belong in other sections. For example, eligibility petitions are found in the Conference Council meeting minutes as well in their own section. Conference Council meeting minutes also frequently include Executive Director's reports, and other committee reports such as the Appraisal, Drug Enforcement, Basketball Coaches, Rose Bowl Management, and Coaches Committees. Meeting agendas are also found with the correspondence files.
The Collection is open for research use.
The PAC-10 and NCAA records of Intercollegiate Athletics were received at the Washington State University Libraries as two accessions. In 1982, faculty representative Edward Bennett transferred files that were in his possession, (MS82-22) and in 1988, the office of Director of Intercollegiate Athletics transferred its files (UA88-42). As the two accessions appeared to be parts of the same original record series, the two were combined.
Washington State University. Sports.
Pacific-10 Conference--History--Archives.
College sports--Washington (State)--Archives
Washington (State); Colleges and Universities; Sports and Recreation; Moving Images
- WSU Files, 1
  - WSU Athletic Department Correspondence
    - 1954-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1981 (Jan.-June) (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1981 (July-Dec.) (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 1982 (Jan.-July) (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - 1982 (Aug.-Dec.) (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - 1983 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Date unknown (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - WSU Women's Athletics Correspondence
    - 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - 1974-1977 (none for 1969-1973) (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - 1979 (Jan.-Feb.) (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - 1979 (Mar.-Dec.) (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - 1981 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - 1982 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Date unknown (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - AIAW handbook, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Women's athletics pamphlets from AIAW and AAWU (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - WSU Athletic Council Meeting Minutes
    - 1957-1968 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - 1970-1982 (none for 1969) (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Eligibility certificates, 1959-1971 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Menøs basketball rosters, 1976-1981 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - NCAA vs. AAU (includes Gerry Lindgren case), 1965 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Pamphlet - "United States Olympic Crisis", 1972 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Search committee - head football coach, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Search committee - asst. athletic director - Cougar Club, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Search committee - assoc. athletic director - operations, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Search committee - head volleyball coach, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Wiscavage hearing, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Simmons hearing, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Material for athletic council survey for Pres. Terrell, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - State of WA Council on Higher Ed - financing of athletics, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Conference survey of WSU athletics 1939 (oversize; located at box 8, folder 204) (Box [8], Folder [204])
- : AAWU/PAC-8/PAC-10 Files, 2
  - AAWU/PAC-8/PAC-10 Correspondence
    - 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - (none for 1961), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - 1963 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - 1964 (Jan.-June) (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - 1964 (July-Dec.) (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - 1965 (Jan.-June) (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - 1965 (July-Dec.) (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - 1966 (Jan.-May) (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - 1966 (June-Dec.) (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - 1967 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - AAWU correspondence date unknown (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - 1968 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - 1969 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - 1970 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - 1971 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - 1972 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - 1973 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - 1975 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - 1976 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - 1977 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - 1980 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - 1981 (Jan.-Aug.) (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - 1981 (Sept.-Dec.) (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - 1982 (Jan.-May) (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - 1982 (June-Dec.) (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - PAC-8/PAC-10 correspondence date unknown (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - AAWU/PAC-8/PAC-10 Council meeting minutes
    - 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - 1966-1967 (none for 1965) (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - 1968 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - 1969 (Box 3, Folder 84)
      (includes agendas)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - 1972 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - 1973 (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - 1974 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - 1975 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - 1976 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - 1977 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - 1980 (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - 1981 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - 1982 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - AAWU/PAC-8/PAC-10 Administrative Committee meeting minutes
    - 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - 1964, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 98)
      (only 2 agendas for 1965),(includes agendas)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - 1977 (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - 1982 (Box 4, Folder 106)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Presidents and chancellors meeting minutes, 1966-1982 (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - "Presentation of Rose Bowl information" PAC-10 and Big Ten (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - PAC-8 executive director's report, 1971-1976 (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - PAC-8/PAC-10 executive director's report, 1977-1981 (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - Presidents, chancellors, and council meetings, 1962-1981 (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Rose bowl management committee meeting minutes, 1963-1982 (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Table of contents for council and admin. comm., 1977-1982 (Box 4, Folder 113)
    - PAC-8/PAC-10 rules interpretations memos, 1972-1982 (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - PAC-10 executive director searches - mostly, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - AAWU financial statement, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 116)
    - AAWU financial statement, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - AAWU financial statement, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 118)
    - AAWU/PAC-8 financial statements, 1965-1972 (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - PAC-8/PAC-10 financial statements, 1973-1981 (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - PIOB financial statement, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 121)
    - Theodore Roosevelt award (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - AAWU work program, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 123)
  - AAWU/PAC-8/PAC-10 Press Releases
    - 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - 1966 (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - 1967 (Box 4, Folder 126)
    - 1968 (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - 1969 (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - 1970 (Box 5, Folder 129)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 130)
    - 1979-1982 (none for 1973-1978) (Box 5, Folder 131)
  - AAWU Letters of Intent
    - 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 133)
  - AAWU/PAC-8/PAC-10 Eligibility Petitions
    - 1960-1962 (Box 5, Folder 134)
    - 1963 (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - 1964 (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - 1965 (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - 1966 (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - 1967 (Box 5, Folder 139)
    - 1968 (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - 1969 (Box 5, Folder 141)
    - 1970 (Box 5, Folder 142)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 143)
    - 1973 (Box 5, Folder 144)
    - 1974 (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - (\#1-75 - 40-75), 1975 (Box 5, Folder 146)
    - (\#41-75 -), 1975 (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - 1976 (Box 5, Folder 148)
    - 1977 (Box 5, Folder 149)
    - 1978 (Box 5, Folder 150)
    - (\#1-79 - 32-79), 1979 (Box 5, Folder 151)
    - (\#33-79 -), 1979 (Box 5, Folder 152)
    - (\#2-80 - 43-80), 1980 (Box 5, Folder 153)
    - (\#58-80 -), 1980 (Box 5, Folder 154)
    - Date unknown (Box 5, Folder 155)
    - AAWU/PAC-8/PAC-10 booklets (Box 5, Folder 156)
- NCAA Files, 3
  - NCAA Correspondence
    - 1959 (Box 6, Folder 157)
    - 1960 (Box 6, Folder 158)
    - 1961 (Box 6, Folder 159)
    - 1962 (Box 6, Folder 160)
    - 1963 (Box 6, Folder 161)
    - 1964 (Box 6, Folder 162)
    - 1965 (Box 6, Folder 163)
    - 1966 (Box 6, Folder 164)
    - 1967 (Box 6, Folder 165)
    - 1968 (Box 6, Folder 166)
    - 1969 (Box 6, Folder 167)
    - 1970 (Box 6, Folder 168)
    - 1971 (Box 6, Folder 169)
    - 1972 (Box 6, Folder 170)
    - 1973 (Box 6, Folder 171)
    - 1974 (Box 6, Folder 172)
    - 1975 (Box 6, Folder 173)
    - 1976 (Box 6, Folder 174)
    - 1977 (Box 6, Folder 175)
    - 1978 (Box 6, Folder 176)
    - 1979 (Box 6, Folder 177)
    - 1980 (Box 6, Folder 178)
    - 1981 (Box 6, Folder 179)
    - 1982 (Box 6, Folder 180)
    - 1983 (Box 6, Folder 181)
    - Date unknown (Box 6, Folder 182)
  - "NCAA News" newsletter
    - 1967, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 183)
    - 1975 (Box 6, Folder 184)
    - 1976 (Box 6, Folder 185)
    - 1977 (Box 6, Folder 186)
    - 1978 (Box 6, Folder 187)
    - 1979 (Box 6, Folder 188)
    - 1980 (Box 6, Folder 189)
    - 1981 (Box 6, Folder 190)
    - 1982 - Jan. 1983 (Box 6, Folder 191)
  - NCAA Booklets
    - Convention booklets, 1963, 1967, 1968, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 192)
    - Convention booklets, 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 193)
    - Convention booklet, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 194)
    - Manuals, 1965, 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 195)
    - Sports and rec. programs directories (Box 7, Folder 196)
    - Television plan booklets (Box 7, Folder 197)
    - Annual report, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 198)
    - Misc. NCAA booklets (Box 7, Folder 199)
    - Misc. NCAA booklets (Box 7, Folder 200)
    - Misc. NCAA booklets (Box 7, Folder 201)
  - Miscellaneous Booklets
    - National Football Foundation booklets (Box 7, Folder 202)
    - Miscellaneous booklets (Box 7, Folder 203)
    - Conference survey of WSU athletics, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 204)